<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
 <!--
Viktoryia Maskevich
vmaskevi@my.smccd.edu
CIS 114
ScientificAmerican.xml
Midterm 2
04/15/2011
-->
 <rss version="0.92">
 <channel><language>en-us</language><title>Scientific American</title><image><title>Scientific American</title><link>http://www.sciam.com/</link><width>144</width><url>http://www.sciam.com/media/logo/SAlogo_144px.gif</url><height>45</height></image><link>http://www.sciam.com/</link><copyright>Copyright 1996-2011 Scientific American</copyright><description>Science news and technology updates from Scientific American</description><item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 17:05:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>What makes old beer taste bad? Why, it&apos;s the trans-iso-alpha acids, of course</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=what-makes-old-beer-taste-bad-why-i-2011-04-15</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;  Beer , for the most part, is not like wine--it does not improve with age. Quite the contrary, in fact. Old beer is a comparatively unpalatable shadow of its former self-- skunky in odor , bitter in aftertaste.   &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=what-makes-old-beer-taste-bad-why-i-2011-04-15&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Chemistry,Everyday Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 15:09:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Recession cuts U.S. and Russia 2009 greenhouse emissions</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=recession-cuts-us-and-russia-2009-g</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;By Alister Doyle, Environment Correspondent&lt;/p&gt;                                &lt;p&gt;OSLO (Reuters) - U.S. and Russian greenhouse gas emissions fell in 2009, according to data submitted to the United Nations, as economic decline cut the use of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=recession-cuts-us-and-russia-2009-g&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 15:02:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Industry Challenges Study that Natural Gas &apos;Fracking&apos; Adds Excessively to Greenhouse Effect</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=industry-challenges-study-natural-gas-excessively-adds-greenhouse-effect</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;By Richard Lovett of   Nature   magazine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;In the calculus of global warming, natural gas is generally considered to be preferable to coal as a fuel. &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=industry-challenges-study-natural-gas-excessively-adds-greenhouse-effect&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Society &amp; Policy,More Science,Energy Technology,Clean Air Policy,Climate,Environment</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 14:30:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Saharan dust feeds Atlantic Ocean plankton</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/gallery_directory.cfm?photo_id=5A67FD07-9703-426E-06568AE56DA1FA85</link>
  
  <description> &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/gallery_directory.cfm?photo_id=5A67FD07-9703-426E-06568AE56DA1FA85&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Space,Environment,Ecology,More Science,Biology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>One Percent of U.S. Coal Plants Closed to Avoid Pollution</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=one-percent-us-coal-plants-closed-avoid-pollution</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the nation&apos;s largest coal-burning utilities said yesterday it will shutter 18 of its coal-fired boilers and pay billions to rein in pollutants at many of its remaining units, underscoring the evolving energy landscape in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move by the Tennessee Valley Authority will result in nearly 1 percent of the nation&apos;s coal-fired power capacity going offline by the end of 2018, including 1,000 megawatts of coal-fired power TVA said it planned to retire last year. TVA&apos;s landmark deal with a suite of states and environmental groups and U.S. EPA resolves a number of lingering violation complaints EPA brought against the company for allegedly failing to comply with Clean Air Act pollution control requirements at 11 of its plants.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=one-percent-us-coal-plants-closed-avoid-pollution&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Society &amp; Policy,Everyday Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 11:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Smoking Weeds: Stopping Fast-Spreading, Invasive Reeds without Chemicals Takes Perseverance</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=getting-rid-fast-spreading-non-native-reeds-without-chemicals</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;  Dear EarthTalk : We have an invasion of phragmites in the wetlands bordering our neighborhood. I understand they are a non-native plant that, if left unchecked, will overrun the whole ecosystem. How does one remedy this situation in an eco-friendly way?  --Jeff Willets, via e-mail &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fast-growing, fast-spreading phragmites ( Phragmites australis ), which most of us know as common reeds, can present a major problem in freshwater and tidal wetland habitats. This is especially so in eastern U.S. states along the Atlantic coast, but also increasingly across much of the Midwest and parts of the Pacific Northwest and southern Canada. While some subspecies of the plant may actually be native to our continent, it is non-native varieties that run rampant across North American wetlands today, presenting a formidable threat to biodiversity, crowding out other plants that wildlife depend upon for food and shelter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=getting-rid-fast-spreading-non-native-reeds-without-chemicals&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Society &amp; Policy,Ecology,More Science,Environment,Everyday Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 11:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>You (posthumously) light up my life</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=you-posthumously-light-up-my-life-2011-04-15</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Cemetery of the Innocents in Paris was one of the most well known in the city and its grounds were in high demand by those wishing to be buried in a Christian graveyard between the 12th and 18th centuries. While many couldn&amp;rsquo;t afford an actual plot, the majority of corpses ended up in mass graves that held around 1,500 people in each. As the corpse count climbed, several problems arose such as over crowding, putrid odors, and the supposed ability of the air in the cemetery to change the color of fabric and rot meat before one&amp;rsquo;s eyes.    &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=you-posthumously-light-up-my-life-2011-04-15&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Everyday Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Mountain bongo faces extinction after more than a century of decline</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=mountain-bongo-faces-extinction-aft-2011-04-15</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; The world&apos;s largest forest antelope faces almost certain extinction in the wild in as few as 14 years if current population trends continue, according to a  statement  by the Kenya Wildlife Service (KWS).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just 103 critically endangered mountain bongos  (Tragelaphus eurycerus isaaci)  remain in Kenya, the last country where the animals exist in the wild. They live in four scattered and isolated groups, the largest of which numbers 50 individuals. The KWS called the species &amp;quot;possibly the most endangered land mammal south of the Sahara.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=mountain-bongo-faces-extinction-aft-2011-04-15&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Evolution,Society &amp; Policy,Energy &amp; Sustainability,Environment,More Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 09:30:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Tame Your Inner Tiger</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=tame-your-inner-tiger</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;All parents struggle to find the right balance between encouragement and discipline when it comes to raising their kids. This past winter Yale University law professor Amy Chua drew roars of protest when she asserted in her book,  Battle Hymn of the Tiger Mother , that successful parenting entails controlling most aspects of a child&amp;rsquo;s life, from prohibiting playdates and sleepovers to screaming at children for getting grades lower than an A. What does research say about this style of child-rearing?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s no evidence that intrusiveness is appropriate in any culture we&amp;rsquo;ve been to before, including China,&amp;rdquo; says psychologist Brian K. Barber of the University of Tennessee Knoxville. To learn more about how psychological control might vary across the world, Barber and his colleagues interviewed 120 adolescents from five different cultures, including Costa Rica, Thailand and South Africa, and then surveyed another 2,100. Their findings, which they recently submitted to the  Journal of Adolescence , suggest that some of the behavior described in Chua&amp;rsquo;s book, such as insulting kids (she once called her daughter &amp;ldquo;garbage&amp;rdquo;), invalidating their feelings and violating their privacy, correlated with children&amp;rsquo;s depression and antisocial behavior, a finding that matches past research.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=tame-your-inner-tiger&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Mind &amp; Brain,Health,Mind &amp; Brain,Society &amp; Policy,Ethics,Neurological Disorders,Psychiatry,Psychology,Thought &amp; Cognition,Biology,Everyday Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 09:14:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>A year on, Gulf still grapples with BP oil spill</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=a-year-on-gulf-still-grapples-with-BP-oil-spill</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;By Anna Driver and Matthew Bigg&lt;/p&gt;                                &lt;p&gt;VENICE, La./WAVELAND, Mississippi (Reuters) - When a BP oil rig exploded and sank in the Gulf of Mexico last April, killing 11 workers, authorities first reported that no crude was leaking into the ocean.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=a-year-on-gulf-still-grapples-with-BP-oil-spill&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Health,Technology,Ecology,Everyday Science,More Science,Environment,Society &amp; Policy</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 09:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Blaming parents: What I&apos;ve learned and unlearned as a child psychiatrist </title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=blaming-parents-what-ive-learned-an-2011-04-15</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The fact that he&apos;d stopped crying scared me.  Damn rear-facing car seat. I couldn&apos;t see him as I was driving to the hospital at 3 a.m. Now the hospital construction was making it impossible to find the entrance to the emergency room, let alone a place to leave the car.  Getting out of the car and opening the back door, I saw that bubbles had gathered around my infant son&apos;s mouth. His blue lips pushed forward in an odd pucker. His head bobbed violently with the effort of taking air.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh my God,&amp;quot; I said, and ran with him - past the guard desk, down the halls. Arriving at the emergency room triage desk finally, I simply held him up to the nurse, saying, &amp;quot;My son.&amp;quot; Now limp, his skin was speckled blue and white.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=blaming-parents-what-ive-learned-an-2011-04-15&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Health</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 09:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Too Contagious to Fail: Why Bankers Should Think More Like Epidemiologists</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=too-contagious-to-fail</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;What could the study of infectious disease teach us about the 2008 financial crisis? Plenty, argue University of Oxford ecologist Robert M. &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=too-contagious-to-fail&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Health,Chemistry,Environment,Mind &amp; Brain,Medical Technology,Everyday Science,More Science,Thought &amp; Cognition,Ethics,Infectious Diseases,Biology,Society &amp; Policy</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Crab Love Nest</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=crab-love-nest</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Carmela Cuomo thought she had the secret within reach, hidden in a shallow black tank at the NOAA marine fisheries laboratory in Milford, Conn. The horseshoe crabs she had plucked from New Haven Harbor in 2000 trundled about their springtime ritual, digging pits in the sand, laying their eggs and fertilizing them. She was trying to understand what formula of light, food and chemistry induced these 500-million-year-old creatures to breed. But the next year, before she could figure it out, the crabs stopped mating, and the secret eluded her.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cuomo, an environmental scientist at the University of New Haven, continued to search for the answer for 10 years, in the tanks at Milford, at labs at her university, and in a set of aquariums in her own basement. Now, finally, she has begun to unlock the mystery.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=crab-love-nest&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Environment,Everyday Science,Psychology,Evolution,Science Education,Evolutionary Biology,Biology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Dose Detectives: Device Analyzes Radiation Exposure through Teeth and Nails [Slide Show]</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=radiation-detector</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Workers at the stricken Fukushima Daiichi nuclear power plant fighting to keep additional radioactive iodine, cesium, strontium and other harmful elements from being released into the environment are monitored daily for exposure to radiation. The same is true of the  police and firefighters scouring the area within 10 kilometers of the plant  for missing people.   &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=radiation-detector&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Technology,Environment,Health,Medical Technology,Everyday Science,More Science,Biotechnology,Biotechnology,Biology,Society &amp; Policy</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 22:36:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Are Larger Earthquakes a Sign of the Times?</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=are-larger-earthquakes-a-sign</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;   By Sid Perkins for    Nature    magazine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;   Beginning in late 2004, a flurry of massive, tsunami-spawning earthquakes have rocked the world, first slamming Indonesia, then Chile and most recently Japan. &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=are-larger-earthquakes-a-sign&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 21:15:08 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Hunger Hormone Sharpens Shnoz</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/podcast/episode.cfm?id=hunger-hormone-sharpens-shnoz-11-04-14</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;When your stomach&amp;rsquo;s empty, it pumps out the hormone ghrelin, to whet your appetite and get your juices flowing. But ghrelin doesn&amp;rsquo;t just make you crave a bite. It helps you track it down too--by sharpening your sense of smell. That&amp;rsquo;s according to a study out this week in the  Journal of Neuroscience . [Jenny Tong et al., &amp;quot; Ghrelin Enhances Olfactory Sensitivity and Exploratory Sniffing in Rodents and Humans &amp;quot;]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, scientists injected rats with ghrelin, and videotaped their noses. Their sniffers ran on overdrive for several hours following the injection. And the rats could detect fainter scents, too.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/podcast/episode.cfm?id=hunger-hormone-sharpens-shnoz-11-04-14&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Everyday Science,Evolutionary Biology,More Science,Biology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Underground Xenon100 experiment closes in on dark matter&apos;s hiding place</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=underground-xenon100-experiment-clo-2011-04-14</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; A major dark matter experiment has taken a swipe with its technological net in the hopes of catching  some of the elusive particles  that make up the universe&apos;s missing mass, and once again that net has come up empty. But in swiping and missing,  the Xenon100 experiment  has closed in a bit tighter on where dark matter--the invisible stuff theorized to outweigh the ordinary matter in the universe by a factor of five--might be hiding.   &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=underground-xenon100-experiment-clo-2011-04-14&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Space,Cosmology,More Science,Astrophysics,Physics,Technology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 17:16:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Too Hard for Science? The adventures of a biomolecule in a cell</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=too-hard-for-science-the-adventures-2011-04-14</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; Following the motions of a specific molecule inside a cell is no easy task &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; In &amp;quot;Too Hard for Science?&amp;quot; I interview scientists about ideas they would love to explore that they don&apos;t think could be investigated. For instance, they might involve machines beyond the realm of possibility, such as particle accelerators as big as the sun, or they might be completely unethical, such as lethal experiments involving people. This feature aims to look at the impossible dreams, the seemingly intractable problems in science. However, the question mark at the end of &amp;quot;Too Hard for Science?&amp;quot; suggests that nothing might be impossible. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=too-hard-for-science-the-adventures-2011-04-14&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Health,Medical Technology,Biotechnology,Health,Biotechnology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 16:45:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Consider the crayfish: How a claw-full of neurons makes crustaceans crawl [Video]</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=consider-the-crayfish-how-a-claw-fu-2011-04-14</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; Do animals give much thought to voluntary behavior? Before you or I reach for a cup of coffee, we make a conscious--even if barely so--decision to do it. But what about  tiny-brained crustaceans ? How does a  crayfish  decide to be on its way?    &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=consider-the-crayfish-how-a-claw-fu-2011-04-14&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Mind &amp; Brain,Mind &amp; Brain,Everyday Science,Thought &amp; Cognition,Evolution,Evolutionary Biology,Neuroscience,Biology,More Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 16:40:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>A Bicycle Built for None: What Makes a Riderless Bike Stable? [Video]</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=self-stable-bike</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Be kind to your bicycle, for you may need it more than it needs you.   &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=self-stable-bike&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Math,Physics,Automotive Technology,Everyday Science,History of Science,Technology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 16:15:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Women with High Male Hormone Levels Face Sports Ban</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=women-high-male-hormone-levels-sports-ban</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;By Joanna Marchant of   Nature   magazine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;Female athletes may not be eligible to compete as women if they have natural testosterone levels in the male range. &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=women-high-male-hormone-levels-sports-ban&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Health,Ethics,Everyday Science,More Science,Biology,Society &amp; Policy</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 16:10:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Why Do Earthworms Surface After Rain?</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=why-earthworms-surface-after-rain</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Earthworms laying on sidewalks or streets after a heavy spring rain has become commonplace, but why do they do this ... and could they be a travel hazard?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Researchers hypothesize several reasons why heavy rain storms bring crawlers out of their soil homes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=why-earthworms-surface-after-rain&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Biology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 14:55:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Australian mathematicians say some endangered species &quot;not worth saving&quot;</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=australian-mathematicians-say-some-2011-04-14</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; Some endangered species on the brink of extinction might not be worth saving, according to a new algorithm developed by researchers at the University of Adelaide and James Cook University, both in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dubbed the SAFE (species&apos; ability to forestall extinction) index, the formula takes current and minimum viable population sizes into account to determine if it is too costly to save a species from extinction. The research was published online March 30 in the journal  Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment  . &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=australian-mathematicians-say-some-2011-04-14&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Math,Society &amp; Policy,Evolution,More Science,Environment,Everyday Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 11:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Budget Cuts Open Earth Observation Gap</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=budget-cuts-earth-observation-gap</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The fiscal 2011 budget compromise crafted by the White House and congressional leaders would delay a key federal climate and weather satellite program, making a lengthy gap in critical environmental data a near certainty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cuts contained in the 2011 budget plan would push back the launch of the first Joint Polar Satellite System (JPSS) orbiter by at least 18 months past the current 2016 target, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration chief Jane Lubchenco said yesterday.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=budget-cuts-earth-observation-gap&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Everyday Science,Space,Society &amp; Policy</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 09:02:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>7 Ways to Cultivate Your Creativity [Slide Show]</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=creativity-cultivation-unlock-ingenuity</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Creativity is a sought-after commodity among employers and those seeking personal or professional fulfillment. It comes in handy not only while concocting works of art and literature but also in planning a corporate event or devising a new business strategy. Some people seem more naturally open to new ideas and able to put them to innovative uses. Many of these individuals also tend to be a little&amp;hellip;well&amp;hellip;different, as Harvard psychologist Shelley Carson wrote in the  May/June 2011  Scientific American MIND  . But you don&apos;t have to be eccentric to be creative. You don&apos;t even have to be born with a knack for innovation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Psychologists, artists and others have developed tactics and advice for unlocking people&apos;s creative potential (see, for example,  &amp;quot;Let Your Creativity Soar&amp;quot;  by Mariette DiChristina, John Houtz, Julia Cameron and Robert Epstein in  Scientific American MIND,  June/July 2008). In her recent book,  Your Creative Brain: Seven Steps to Maximize Imagination, Productivity and Innovation in Your Life  (Jossey-Bass, 2010), Carson outlined seven different &amp;quot;brainsets,&amp;quot; or mental frameworks, that facilitate original thinking along with tips on how to cultivate these states of mind. Depending on your personality, some of the brainsets below may feel more comfortable than others. The idea here, though, Carson wrote, is to expand your mental horizons by venturing into your  dis comfort zone. The following slides describe each brainset, along with exercises that will help you train your brain to think in these mind-expanding ways.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=creativity-cultivation-unlock-ingenuity&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Mind &amp; Brain,Mind &amp; Brain,Thought &amp; Cognition,Language &amp; Linguistics,Language &amp; Linguistics,Health,More Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 09:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>The Unleashed Mind: Why Creative People Are Eccentric (preview)</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=the-unleashed-mind</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;He is one of the world&amp;rsquo;s best known and most successful entrepreneurs, with hundreds of patents to his name--including the Segway scooter. But you will never see Dean Kamen in a suit and tie: the eccentric inventor dresses almost exclusively in denim. He spent five years in college before dropping out, does not take vacations and has never married. Kamen presides (along with his Ministers of Ice Cream, Brunch and Nepotism) over the Connecticut island kingdom of North Dumpling, which has &amp;ldquo;seceded&amp;rdquo; from the U.S. and dispenses its own currency in units of pi. Visitors are issued a visa form that includes spaces on which to note identifying marks on both their face and buttocks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kamen, who works tirelessly at inspiring kids to pursue careers in science and engineering, is one of many highly creative people whose personal behavior sometimes strikes others as odd. Albert Einstein picked up cigarette butts off the street to get tobacco for his pipe; Howard Hughes spent entire days on a chair in the middle of the supposedly germ-free zone of his Beverly Hills Hotel suite; the composer Robert Schumann believed that his musical compositions were dictated to him by Beethoven and other deceased luminaries from their tombs; and Charles Dickens is said to have fended off imaginary urchins with his umbrella as he walked the streets of London. More recently, we have seen Michael Jackson&amp;rsquo;s preoccupation with rhinoplasty, Salvador Dal&amp;iacute;&amp;rsquo;s affection for dangerous pets and the Icelandic singer Bj&amp;ouml;rk dressed for the Oscars as a swan.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=the-unleashed-mind&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Mind &amp; Brain,Health,Society &amp; Policy,More Science,Evolution,Thought &amp; Cognition,Language &amp; Linguistics,Language &amp; Linguistics,Neuroscience,Psychiatry,Psychology,Biology,Evolutionary Biology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 08:58:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Feed Your Mind</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=feed-your-mind</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;When we launched  Scientific American Mind  as a new publication in 2004, it seemed like a great opportunity to give readers more stories about popular areas of mind and brain research--which, fortuitously, were also booming because of imaging and other advances. What I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize at the time, but probably should have, is how often the findings in our pages would shake loose what I thought I knew about how our gray matter works. In every way, editing this magazine over the years has been, well, mind-expanding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take creativity, the subject of our cover story, &amp;ldquo; The Unleashed Mind ,&amp;rdquo; by Harvard University psychologist Shelley Carson. It is common for people to refer, with a knowing wink, to &amp;ldquo;creative types&amp;rdquo;--and we all know what that means. We think of someone a little &amp;hellip; different from the rest of us workaday sorts. Someone who surprises us with spectacularly odd wardrobe choices but also with amazing insights into problems we are trying to solve.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=feed-your-mind&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Mind &amp; Brain,Society &amp; Policy,Everyday Science,More Science,Thought &amp; Cognition,Evolutionary Biology,Language &amp; Linguistics,Language &amp; Linguistics,Neuroscience,Biology,Evolution</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Social networking and energy conservation: What went wrong?</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=social-networking-and-energy-conser-2011-04-14</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; It was a match made in geek heaven. Combine the hottest online activity--social networking--with the biggest environmental challenge--energy conservation--and you get something yummier than peanut butter and chocolate. It&apos;s not just a mashup of buzzwords, either. Most of us pat ourselves on the back about our energy-saving ways. Sure, we have our vices, but doesn&apos;t our routine greenness make up for the occasional slippage, be it bright kitchen lights or an extra degree on the thermostat? Only by  talking to neighbors and friends  might we discover we aren&apos;t so virtuous after all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That&apos;s what social networks could be good for. People&apos;s competitive instincts might well be the country&apos;s biggest energy source. Also, there&apos;s so much confusing and conflicting information out there that it would help to be able to share our experiences of what works and what doesn&apos;t. In the past couple of years, a number of sites sprouted up to meet this demand.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=social-networking-and-energy-conser-2011-04-14&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Energy Technology,Green Living,Energy Technology,Alternative Energy Technology,Alternative Energy Technology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 07:30:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Why Are Asthma Rates Soaring?</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=why-are-asthma-rates-soaring</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Asthma rates have been surging around the globe over the past three decades, and for a long time researchers thought they had a good idea of what might be fueling the increase: the world we live in is just a little too clean. According to this notion--known as the hygiene hypothesis--exposure in early childhood to infectious agents programs the immune system to mount differing highly effective defenses against disease-causing viruses, bacteria and parasites. Better sanitary conditions deprive the immune system of this training, so that for reasons that are still unclear, the body pounces on harmless particles--such as dust and ragweed--as if they were deadly threats. The resulting allergic reaction leads to the classic signs of asthma: chronic inflammation or swelling of the airways and acute spasms of those passageways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or so the thinking went. Although a lot of data support the hygiene hypothesis for allergies, the same cannot be said for asthma. Contrary to expectations, asthma rates have skyrocketed in urban areas in the U.S. that are not particularly clean. Moreover, the big increase in asthma rates in developed countries did not kick off until the 1980s--well after general sanitary conditions in the richer parts of the world had improved. And some studies are beginning to show that far from protecting children from asthma, respiratory infections in early childhood may actually be a risk factor for it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=why-are-asthma-rates-soaring&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Health,Environment,Society &amp; Policy,Pharmaceuticals,More Science,Evolution,Evolutionary Biology,Infectious Diseases,Biology,Everyday Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 07:01:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Cracking a Century-Old Enigma</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=cracking-a-century-old-enigma</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;For someone who died at the age of 32, the largely self-taught Indian mathematician Srinivasa Ramanujan left behind an impressive legacy. Number theorists have now finally managed to make sense of one of his more enigmatic statements, written just one year before his death in 1920.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The statement concerned the deceptively simple concept of partitions. Partitions are subdivisions of a whole number into smaller ones. For example, for the number 5 there are seven options:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=cracking-a-century-old-enigma&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Math,Mind &amp; Brain,Society &amp; Policy,Thought &amp; Cognition,Science Education,Language &amp; Linguistics,Language &amp; Linguistics,History of Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Make or Breaker: Can a Tsunami Warning System Save Lives During an Earthquake?</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=can-tsunami-warning-system-save-lives-eartquake</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;It was a through-the-looking-glass moment for Chris Goldfinger, sitting in a meeting about Sumatran earthquakes on a recent Friday afternoon in Chiba, Japan, on the outskirts of Tokyo. The floor started heaving as if a switch flipped. That terrible shaking turned out to be the magnitude 9.0 Sendai temblor, tsunami-maker and devastator.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;We felt pretty safe,&amp;quot; says Goldfinger, director of Oregon State University&apos;s Active Tectonics and Seafloor Mapping Lab, &amp;quot;but, oddly, still had time to run outside and ride through four or five minutes of mainshock. That was a very long time for the Earth to feel like the ocean.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=can-tsunami-warning-system-save-lives-eartquake&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Technology,Physics,Energy &amp; Sustainability,Everyday Science,More Science,Environment,Society &amp; Policy</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 06:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Fossil footprints of early modern humans found in Tanzania </title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=fossil-footprints-of-early-modern-h-2011-04-14</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;MINNEAPOLIS--Newly discovered fossil footprints at a site in northern Tanzania on the shore of Lake Natron capture a moment in time around 120,000 years ago when a band of 18 humans--early members of our own species,  Homo sapiens --traipsed across wet volcanic ash to an unknown destination. Brian Richmond of George Washington University unveiled the stunning find here on April 13 at the annual meeting of the Paleoanthropology Society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Footprints are extremely rare in the human fossil record, and highly prized for the unique information they can reveal about the anatomy and behavior of our ancient relatives. Richmond and his colleagues found the new prints--more than 350 in all--in 2010 at the site, called Engare Sero. No animal prints were among them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=fossil-footprints-of-early-modern-h-2011-04-14&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Evolution,Society &amp; Policy,Evolutionary Biology,Archaeology &amp; Paleontology,More Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 19:11:08 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Paul Davies: Physics Could Help Fight Cancer</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/podcast/episode.cfm?id=paul-davies-physics-could-help-figh-11-04-13</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Only 10 percent of people die from primary tumors. The real problem is when it spreads around the body. The problem of metastases.&amp;rdquo; Arizona State University&amp;rsquo;s  Paul Davies , speaking at the Penn Club in New York. I don&amp;rsquo;t think we need to cure cancer. In fact, I don&amp;rsquo;t really think of cancer as a disease as much as an alternative form of living matter. We don&amp;rsquo;t need to cure it, we just need to manage it for long enough that people die of something else.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The cosmologist was asked to study cancer by the National Cancer Institute . &amp;ldquo;When cancer cells spread around the body, this is a physics problem. These cells are microscopic bodies being swept along in this raging torrent. They wriggle around, they latch on to surfaces, they drill their way through. This is the sort of language that physicists and engineers can understand. Cancer research is dominated by genetics and biochemistry. That&amp;rsquo;s why we have the therapies, genetic and chemotherapy, as the main approaches. I think that we can open up a whole new frontier just by thinking about the problem in a totally different way.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/podcast/episode.cfm?id=paul-davies-physics-could-help-figh-11-04-13&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Health,Health,Cosmology,Everyday Science,More Science,Biology,Physics</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 19:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Cod Ranching Could Keep Fishermen Flush</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=cod-ranching-could-keep-fisher-flush</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;By Daniel Cressey of   Nature   magazine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;Ranching cod off the coast of Iceland is far more financially sensible than conventional fishing methods or keeping the fish in cages, according to a new analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;Fish ranching -- where the animals are free to roam but trained to return to a certain point so they can be caught -- could one day become a significant part of global fisheries, fitting between traditional catching and aquaculture, says Bj&amp;#246;rn Bj&amp;#246;rnsson, the lead author of the study, published in Marine Policy on 1 April. &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=cod-ranching-could-keep-fisher-flush&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Society &amp; Policy,Green Living,Environment,More Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 17:44:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Plant Strife: Satellite measurements show declining phytoplankton in ocean currents</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/gallery_directory.cfm?photo_id=50C370F6-0258-97D5-4AE8EAA3B6C3D136</link>
  
  <description> &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/gallery_directory.cfm?photo_id=50C370F6-0258-97D5-4AE8EAA3B6C3D136&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Space,Environment,Ecology,More Science,Biology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 17:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Schizophrenia &apos;in a Dish&apos;</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=schizophrenia-in-a-dish</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;By Ewen Callaway of   Nature   magazine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;Before committing suicide at the age of 22, an anonymous man with schizophrenia donated a biopsy of his skin cells to research. &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=schizophrenia-in-a-dish&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Health,Biotechnology,Biology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 13:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Did Lucy&apos;s species butcher animals? </title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=did-lucys-species-butcher-animals-2011-04-13</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; MINNEAPOLIS--In August 2010 archaeologists announced that they had discovered evidence that pushed back the  origin of butchery  nearly 800,000 years. Studying bones of cow- and goat-size animals dated to around 3.4 million years ago from a site in Ethiopia  called Dikika , Shannon McPherron of the Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology in Leipzig, Germany, and his colleagues observed several distinctive marks. After conducting an extensive analysis of the marks, the team determined that they resulted from butchery with stone tools, although no implements were recovered at the site. Because the only human remains known from Dikika belong to  Australopithecus afarensis --the species to which the famous Lucy fossil belongs--the researchers concluded  A. afarensis  was the butcher.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The discovery made a big splash, because scientists thought stone tool use and butchery originated with human ancestors more advanced than Lucy&apos;s kind. Furthermore, according to conventional wisdom,  A. afarensis  relied primarily on plant foods.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=did-lucys-species-butcher-animals-2011-04-13&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Evolution,Biology,History of Science,Mind &amp; Brain,Thought &amp; Cognition,Society &amp; Policy,More Science,Archaeology &amp; Paleontology,Technology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 11:26:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>U.S. on track to meet 1 million plug-in autos goal</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=us-on-track-to-meet-1-million-</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;DETROIT (Reuters) - President Barack Obama&apos;s goal of having 1 million plug-in vehicles on U.S. roads by 2015 is on its way to being met, a Department of Energy official said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;                                &lt;p&gt;&quot;It&apos;s looking good,&quot; said Assistant Energy Secretary David Sandalow when asked by reporters on the chances of meeting the goal set by Obama.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=us-on-track-to-meet-1-million-&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Technology,Society &amp; Policy,Everyday Science,More Science,Energy Technology,Environment,Alternative Energy Technology,Clean Air Policy,Automotive Technology,Energy Technology,Alternative Energy Technology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 11:15:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Smart Grid Works for Utilities, but Not Yet for Consumers</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=smart-grid-works-utilities-not-yet-consumers</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;When a frigid cold wave knocked out 50 power plants in Texas during February&apos;s Super Bowl week, utilities had to impose rolling blackouts across entire communities with a &amp;quot;blunt ax,&amp;quot; said Robert Shapard, CEO of Dallas-based Oncor, the state&apos;s largest transmission company.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next year, when Oncor completes installing 3.4 million smart meters throughout its system, future rolling blackouts could be tailored to protect nursing homes, compressor stations that keep natural gas flowing and other priority facilities, Shapard said. In theory, a &amp;quot;smart&amp;quot; rolling blackout could even bypass homes with patients on ventilators, because the utility can control power delivery to individual meters, he said.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=smart-grid-works-utilities-not-yet-consumers&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Society &amp; Policy,Everyday Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 11:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Corporate Whitewash?: Why Do Cleaning Product-Makers Keep Most of Their Ingredients Secret?</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=toxic-ingredients-cleaning-products</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;  Dear EarthTalk : Why don&amp;rsquo;t cleaning products have to list their ingredients? Are these products tested for what they might do to your health?  --Patricia Greenville, Bethel, Conn.    &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=toxic-ingredients-cleaning-products&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Everyday Science,Green Living,Society &amp; Policy,More Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 08:10:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Regeneration: The axolotl story</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=regeneration-the-axolotl-story-2011-04-13</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, the science community was set a-buzz with a new study that showcased the unique relationship between salamanders and algae. The research, done by Ryan Kerney at Dalhousie University in Halifax, Canada, found that spotted salamander tissues contained algae embedded within them. The exact purpose of this relationship (which begins when the salamanders are only embryos) is not yet known, and the jury is still out if it is truly a symbiotic relationship or tends towards mutualism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An area of research related to that done by Kerney et al.  is one that has so far managed to stay out of reach: cellular regeneration.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=regeneration-the-axolotl-story-2011-04-13&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Health,Medical Technology,Biotechnology,Biology,Biotechnology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Too Much Information? Noninvasive Genetic Tests for the Unborn</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=too-much-information</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today expectant parents concerned about the diseases that could afflict their unborn children don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of options. Blood tests can determine whether parents carry mutations for such genetic diseases as cystic fibrosis and Tay-Sachs, but they can&amp;rsquo;t determine whether the baby will inherit them. And although fetuses can be tested for Down syndrome and other chromosomal abnormalities using amniocentesis or chorionic villus sampling, about 1 percent of procedures cause miscarriage, so many moms opt out. But thanks to a handful of recent breakthroughs, noninvasive prenatal tests may soon be available that diagnose genetic diseases before birth using samples of a mother&amp;rsquo;s blood--an exciting possibility that also raises difficult questions about how they should be regulated and administered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What makes noninvasive tests possible is that a pregnant woman&amp;rsquo;s blood contains free-floating copies of her fetus&amp;rsquo;s genes, as chemical pathologist Dennis Lo of the Chinese University of Hong Kong discovered in 1997. Last December in  Science Translational Medicine , Lo reported on a method of&amp;nbsp; sequencing individual fetal genes and counting individual fetal chromosomes in a mother&amp;rsquo;s blood to establish whether a fetus carries disease-causing mutations or chromosomal abnormalities. Fetal genes inherited from the mother are identifiable because they are present in higher-than-normal concentrations in the mother&amp;rsquo;s blood; gene variants not shared by the mother are assumed to be inherited from the father. In a follow-up article in the  British Medical Journal , Lo tested his approach on 753 pregnant women. He counted the proportion of DNA molecules found in the mother&amp;rsquo;s blood that were derived from chromosome 21--individuals with Down syndrome have three copies rather than the normal two--and accurately diagnosed 100 percent of the fetuses who would be born with the disorder.&amp;nbsp; The test, Lo says, would prevent &amp;ldquo;98 percent of invasive procedures, such as amniocentesis.&amp;rdquo; The trial did, however, report three false positives, so all positive results would need to be followed up with more invasive tests.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=too-much-information&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Health,Technology,Society &amp; Policy,Everyday Science,More Science,Medical Technology,Science Education,Evolutionary Biology,Biotechnology,Biotechnology,Ethics,Biology,Evolution</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 07:01:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>How &quot;Inadmissible&quot; Brain Scans Can Still Influence the Courts</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=gazzaniga-inadmissible-brain-scans-influence-courts</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The world of law as practiced in the real world is far removed from that usually discussed by law professors and philosophers or shown on television and in movies. In idealized or fictional cases the law always operates formally and may seem to pursue some abstract quest for justice. In the everyday practice of law, however, things work differently--it is all about cobbling together the most compelling and convincing story possible either for or against a defendant. Attorneys will shoehorn into their arguments any information they can find that might further their ends. The legal system therefore efficiently uses every scrap of relevant data that might pertain to a case--including findings such as brain scans that might not normally be formally admissible during trials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reality is that few criminal cases--only about 3 percent of federal ones and a bit more than 4 percent at the state level--ever go to trial. Normally, after someone is charged with a crime, the prosecution and the defense attorneys engage in confidential plea bargaining away from the courtroom. The plea negotiations are usually conducted informally (although in intense cases, such as those that might involve the death penalty, they can take on the appearance of a condensed sentencing hearing).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=gazzaniga-inadmissible-brain-scans-influence-courts&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Mind &amp; Brain,Thought &amp; Cognition,Neuroscience</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Neuroscience in the Courtroom (preview)</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=neuroscience-in-the-courtroom</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;By a strange coincidence, I was called to jury duty for my very first time shortly after I started as director of a new MacArthur Foundation project exploring the issues that neuro&amp;shy;science raises for the criminal justice system. Eighty of us showed up for selection in a case that involved a young woman charged with driving under the influence, but most of my fellow citizens were excused for various reasons, primarily their own DUI experiences. Finally, I was called to the judge. &amp;ldquo;Tell me what you do,&amp;rdquo; he said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I am a neuroscientist,&amp;rdquo; I answered, &amp;ldquo;and I have actually done work relevant to what goes on in a courtroom. For example, I have studied how false memories form, the nature of addiction, and how the brain regulates behavior.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=neuroscience-in-the-courtroom&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Mind &amp; Brain,Technology,Society &amp; Policy,Everyday Science,More Science,Science Education,Biotechnology,Language &amp; Linguistics,Neuroscience,Psychiatry,Psychology,Thought &amp; Cognition,Biotechnology,Biology,Language &amp; Linguistics</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 04:27:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>China may freeze nuclear approvals until 2012</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=china-may-freeze-nuclear-appro</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; BEIJING, April 13 (Reuters) - China&apos;s suspension of nuclearproject approvals, put in place in the wake of Japan&apos;s nuclear &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=china-may-freeze-nuclear-appro&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Environment,Society &amp; Policy,Everyday Science,Energy Technology,Energy &amp; Sustainability,Alternative Energy Technology,Alternative Energy Technology,Energy Technology,Technology,More Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2011 19:40:08 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Lawrence Krauss: Students Need to Learn Effective Failure</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/podcast/episode.cfm?id=lawrence-krauss-students-need-to-le-11-04-12</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;One of the things that amazed me was when we brought business people back to say, &amp;lsquo;What don&amp;rsquo;t we teach you in school,&amp;rsquo; these were physicists who became business people. We didn&amp;rsquo;t teach students how to fail effectively.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arizona State University theoretical physicist  Lawrence Krauss . Along with other researchers, university presidents, and reporters, Krauss discussed science and tech policy recently at the Penn Club in New York City. He talked about how he had developed a program &amp;ldquo;in  physics entrepreneurship . Which the business school dean at the time said was an oxymoron. But I don&amp;rsquo;t think so. The point is that what we do throughout our whole education system is give students solvable problems. In fact they&amp;rsquo;re guaranteed to be solvable, from problem sets in first-year physics to, in fact, a PhD.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/podcast/episode.cfm?id=lawrence-krauss-students-need-to-le-11-04-12&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Society &amp; Policy,Science Education,More Science,Physics</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2011 18:00:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Coast Benefits: NASA Announces Retirement Homes for Space Shuttles</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=shuttle-disposition</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The launching and landing of space shuttles has always been a fairly coastal affair: The shuttles take off from Florida and almost always touch down in Florida or California. (Once, in 1982, a shuttle landed at New Mexico&apos;s White Sands Space Harbor.) NASA is continuing that coastal tradition with  the placement of its retired and retiring shuttles , whose final homes were announced April 12. The three shuttles will be displayed in Florida, Los Angeles and Virginia, and a test-flight shuttle that never reached orbit will go to New York City.   &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=shuttle-disposition&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Space,Physics,Space Exploration,Society &amp; Policy,More Science,History of Science,Technology</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2011 17:30:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Octopuses and squids are damaged by noise pollution</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=octopuses-and-squid-are-damaged-by-2011-04-12</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; Not only can  squids  and octopuses sense sound, but as it turns out, these and other so-called cephalopods might be harmed by growing noise pollution in our oceans--from sources such as offshore drilling, ship motors,  sonar use  and pile driving.    &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=octopuses-and-squid-are-damaged-by-2011-04-12&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>More Science,Environment,Mind &amp; Brain,Technology,Society &amp; Policy,Everyday Science,Biology,More Science,Evolution,Energy &amp; Sustainability,Evolutionary Biology,Ecology,Neuroscience</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2011 16:15:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Is Fukushima really as bad as Chernobyl?</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=is-fukushima-really-as-bad-as-chern-2011-04-12</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p&gt; One month to the day after the devastating  twin blows  of a magnitude 9.0 earthquake and subsequent 15-meter tall tsunami, Japanese officials have reclassified the accident at the Fukushima Daiichi nuclear power plant at the highest possible level. The  partial meltdown  of three reactors and at least two spent fuel pools, along with multiple hydrogen explosions at the site now rate a 7 on the International Nuclear Event Scale--a level previously affixed only to the meltdown and explosion at Chernobyl.   &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=is-fukushima-really-as-bad-as-chern-2011-04-12&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Energy &amp; Sustainability,Physics,Technology,Society &amp; Policy,Everyday Science,Energy Technology,Alternative Energy Technology,Alternative Energy Technology,Climate,Energy Technology,Environment,More Science</category>
  </item>
  
  <item>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2011 15:17:00 EST</pubDate>
  
  <title>Radiation Release Will Hit Marine Life</title>
  <link>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=radiation-release-will-hit-marine-life</link>
  
  <description>&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;By Quirin Schiermeier of  Nature  magazine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;As radioisotopes pour into the sea from the crippled Fukushima Daiichi nuclear plant, one reassuring message has been heard over and over again: the Pacific Ocean is a big place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;That the isotopes will be vastly diluted is not in question. &lt;a href=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=radiation-release-will-hit-marine-life&gt;[More]&lt;/a&gt;</description>
  <category>Biology,Society &amp; Policy,Ecology,More Science,Energy &amp; Sustainability,Environment,Everyday Science</category>
  </item></channel>
 </rss>
